Finding Aid to the Durr Friedley Records, 1906-1918 Archives.Friedley.1
The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives
Durr Friedley Records
Bulk, 1914-1917
1906-1918
Archives.Friedley.1
The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives
3.0 Linear feet (8 boxes)
Durr Friedley was a staff member of the Department of Decorative Arts of The Metropolitan Museum of Art from 1911 until 1917, serving as an assistant, Assistant Curator and Acting Curator. Records consist primarily of correspondence regarding prospective Museum acquisitions. Items of special interest include letters concerning the Museum’s acquisition of early American colonial furnishings, later displayed in the American Wing.
Breck, Joseph, b. 1885
Kent, Henry Watson, 1866-1948
Scope and Contents note
Records include letters regarding potential Museum acquisitions exchanged by Durr Friedley with dealers and private owners of decorative arts objects. There are also some letters from the desks of other Decorative Arts Department staff, notably Assistant Curator Russell A. Plimpton (see Series 2). Prominent dealers and collectors represented include Duveen Brothers, Judge A.T. Clearwater and White, Allom and Company. There are a few personal letters, and a small amount of correspondence from before and after Friedley’s service at the Museum. Also included are collection inventory lists, handwritten notes regarding museum objects, photographs and typescript essays by Friedley and other Museum staff. There is substantial documentation regarding the acquisition by the Museum of colonial interiors and period rooms, and planning for the proposed American Wing. The records also include correspondence between Friedley and other members of the Museum administration including Secretary Henry Watson Kent and Director Edward Robinson.
Related Archival Materials note
The records include correspondence relating to many objects eventually acquired by the Museum; when it has been possible to identify these, a note including the object accession number has been added to the relevant entry in the Container List. The Museum Archives or curatorial departments may have additional documentation regarding these objects. Consult Archives staff for further information. Additional files of interest include:
Durr Friedley Correspondence File, Office of the Secretary Records, The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives.
Russell A. Plimpton Correspondence File, Office of the Secretary Records, The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives.
Arrangement note
Prior to processing, the Durr Friedley Records were organized into three series. The first was Durr Friedley correspondence and subject files dating mostly from 1911-1916, but also including a few earlier documents. The second was Durr Friedley correspondence and subject files dating from 1916-1917. The third series was correspondence and subject files of Russell A. Plimpton. The Plimpton series has been maintained while the two Friedley series have been integrated because of general similarities in content and the presence of correspondence that overlapped the chronological break.
Presently, the Durr Friedley Records consist of two series:
Series 1. Durr Friedley Files Series 2. Russell A. Plimpton Files
Both series are arranged alphabetically by corporate name, personal name or subject. Documents within files are arranged chronologically.
Biographical/Historical note
Curator and artist Durr Friedley (1888-1938) was born in Indianapolis, Indiana and received a degree in Fine Arts from Harvard University in 1911. (At Harvard and later in life his surname was spelled Freedley; in records from his time at The Metropolitan Museum of Art it consistently appears as Friedley.) He joined the staff of the Metropolitan Museum of Art in October, 1911, as an assistant in the Department of Decorative Arts. In 1912, after favorable recommendations by colleagues, Friedley was appointed Assistant Curator. He was promoted to Acting Curator in 1914 when the department’s Curator, Dr. Wilhelm R. Valentiner, took a leave of absence to enlist in the German army. Valentiner resigned from the Metropolitan in 1917 and Friedley was offered the post of Curator, but he declined and instead announced his own departure from the Museum.
During his time at the Museum, Friedley was involved with the acquisition and exhibition of a wide range of decorative arts objects. He corresponded extensively with collectors and dealers who owned items of interest to the Museum, and assessed objects under consideration by the Purchasing Committee of the Board of Trustees. Towards the end of his tenure, he worked intensively on the acquisition of colonial American interiors and objects intended for exhibition in the Museum’s planned American Wing. Shortly after leaving the Metropolitan, Friedley drew a set of architectural plans for the proposed American Wing, but they were never used.
In 1918, Friedley served in the U.S. Army as a member of the Aviation Section, U.S. Signal Corps (renamed in May 1918 the Division of Military Aeronautics) painting camouflage on war planes. During the 1920s he spent time in Europe as a portrait painter. He eventually returned to the United States and settled in Newport, Rhode Island, where he continued his career as a portrait painter and muralist. He was commissioned to paint the interiors of the Memorial Chapel at the Seaman’s Church Institute of Newport in 1930. Friedley died in a car accident in March of 1938 at the age of fifty. Memorial exhibitions of his artwork were held at the John Herron Art Institute (now the Indianapolis Museum of Art) in November 1938 and at the Walker Galleries in New York City in early 1939.
Conditions Governing Access note
Archives staff regarding permission to quote or reproduce.
Bibliography
Klaiman, Marianna Garthwaite & Wagner, Mary Kennedy, “Durr Freedley: An American master in English Art” The Magazine Antiques. June 2006; 169,6. Tomkins, Calvin. Merchants and Masterpieces: The Story of the Metropolitan Museum of Art. New York: Henry Holt and Company, 1989.
Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.). American Wing.; Correspondence; Decorative arts; Decorative Arts--United States--History-20th Century--Exhibitions; Decorative arts--United States.
- Series 1. Durr Friedley Files, Bulk, 1914-1917; 1906-1917
  - A, 1912-1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Regarding January-May 1915 letters from Charles Allom see also: Swan Room blueprints in Museum Archives flat files, and White, Allom & Company letters in White-Wy, 1912-1917 B.6/F.8.
  - Altman Guide, n.d (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - American Art Galleries, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ames, Frederic A., 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Arnold Seligmann, Rey & Company, Inc., 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes February 1917 letters regarding Museum accessions 17.40.1-2
  - Ba-Bl, 1911-1917 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Barnard, George Gray, 1913-1917 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Barney, Charles T., 1912 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Barney, James Whitney, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    See also: P.W. French & Company, 1915-1917 B.4/F.16
  - Beilouny, Gabriel, 1914-1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bennett, J. Albert, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Birckhead, Mrs. P.M., 1917 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Blanks, purchase - Miscellaneous drafts and duplicates, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Blumenthal, George, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bo-By, 1914-1917 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Breck, Joseph - Bulletin writings, 1916,1918 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Breck, Joseph - Miscellaneous writings, n.d (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bowler House (Portsmith, R.I.), 1916 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ca-Com, 1911-1917 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Cabot House (Beverly, Mass.), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    See also Cousins, Frank 1912-1915 B.2/F.7
  - Canessa, C. & E., 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Carr, H.W., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ceramics Report - Garrett Chatfield Pier, 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Clearwater, Hon. A.T., 1913-1917 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Coles, Elizabeth U. - bequest, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    See also: Office of the Secretary Records Correspondence Files F.1-8 of Coles, Mrs. William - Collection, reagrding museum accession 92.1.*
  - Colton House (Longmeadow, Mass.), 1916 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Con-Cu, 1912-1916 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Coomaraswamy, Ananda, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cooper Union, n.d (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cornelius, C. O., 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cousins, Frank, 1912-1915 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    See also: Flint, Frank, 1915-1916 B.2/F.18
    See also: Cabot House (Beverly, Mass.), 1917 B.1/F.22
  - Da- Dob, 1911-1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Davis, Theodore M., 1911-1915 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - de Forest, Lockwood, 1912-1917 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes Oct. 22-Dec. 17 1917 letters from Mr. J. Spielberg regarding museum accessions 17.32.1-55 and 17.34.1-3
  - de Forest, Mrs. Emily & Robert W., 1914-1917 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dod-Dy, 1912-1917 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Duveen Brothers, 1915-1917 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    See also: Edson Bradley letters concerning tapestries in Bo-By, 1914-1917 B.1/F.17
  - E, 1912-1917 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Includes June 11, 1917 letter from Thomas Rush regarding museum accession 17.103*
  - F, 1912-1917 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Includes December 23, 1915 letter from Durr Friedley to Mrs. William J. Fitzgerald regarding museum accession 26.57*
  - Fergusona and other Oriental collections., 1912 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Fixtures - Metal Display, n.d (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Flint, Frank, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    See also: Cousins, Frank ,1912-1915 B.2/F.7
  - Friedley, Durr, 1915-1917 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Primarily correspondence to and from Friedley and members of the Decorative Arts Dept. during periods when Friedley was away from the Museum.
  - Friedley, Durr - Bulletin writings, 1912-1917 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Friedley, Durr - Miscellaneous writings, n.d (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Foote, E.T., 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Forbes, Edward, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ga-Grav, 1909-1917 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Gray-Gu, 1911-1917 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Griffith, C.H.E., 1915 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Ha-Hi, 1912-1917 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Halsey, R.T. Haynes, 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Harding, H. Wareham, 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Hearn-Hist, 1910-1917 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Includes Hearn item dated December 9, 1917 regarding museum accession 17.101*
  - Herter Looms, 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Ho-Hy, 1913-1917 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - I, 1912-1917 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Indjoudjian, M., 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Inquires on China, 1911-1914 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - J, 1912-1917 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Includes June 29, 1916 Juillard letter from de Forest Brothers regarding museum accession 19.172*
  - K, 1913-1917 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Kelekian, Dikran, 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Kent, Henry Watson, 1914-1917 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Kindermann, C.H.F., 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - La-Le, 1912-1917 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Labels - Information regarding, 1912-1914 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Li-Ly, 1913-1917 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Library Lists - books added, 1915-1917 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - Lists - miscellaneous, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Ma-Mc, 1913-1917 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - McIlhenny, John D., 1916-1917 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    See also: Meyrick-Jones, F. & L.M., 1916-1917 B.4/F.9
  - Me-Mu, 1912-1917 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Meyrick-Jones, F. & L.M., 1916-1917 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Monif, R. Khan, 1915-1917 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Morgan, J.P. - lists, 1916-1917 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Museum shipping pamphlets, n.d (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - N, 1912-1917 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - O, 1914-1917 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Oatway, H., 1914-1917 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - P.W. French & Company, 1915-1917 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    See also: Barney, James Whitney, 1915-1916 B.1/F.10
  - Pa-Pe, 1912-1916 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Parker, Elizabeth F. & Alice P., 1912-1916 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Parker Seals - imprints, n.d (Box 8)
    See also: Parker, Elizabeth F. & Alice P., 1912-1916 B.4/F.18
  - Ph-Pu, 1912-1917 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Includes July 30, 1915 letter to Mrs. Post and Oct. 21 1915 letter regarding museum accession 30.58.*
  - Q, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - R, 1912-1917 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Rathbone, Fredrick, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Receipts, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Robinson, Edward (Director), 1914-1917 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Sa-Sl, 1914-1917 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Sm-Sw, 1912-1917 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Includes April 4, 1917 letter regarding museum accession 16.46.1-8
  - T, 1912-1917 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Tabbagh, George, 1916-1917 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Tapestry Catalogue, n.d (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Textiles, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
  - Thaw, Mrs. Benjamin, 1915-1916 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - V, 1909, 1914-1917 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Valentiner, Dr. Wilhelm, 1910, 1914, 1917 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Volpi, Elia, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Wa-Whip, 1912-1917 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Includes May 1, 1914 letter regarding Museum accession 15.141a-d
  - Walser, G., 1915-1917 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Warner, Langdon, 1915-1917 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Whit-Wy, 1912-1917 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Regarding White, Allom & Company letters see also: Charles Allom letters in A., 1912-1917 B.1/F.1
  - Writings - miscellaneous, 1916-1917, n.d (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Y-Z, 1913-1917 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Series 2. Russell A. Plimpton Files, Bulk, 1916-1917; 1913-1918; Durr Friedley was a staff member of the Department of Decorative Arts of The Metropolitan Museum of Art from 1911 until 1917, serving as an assistant, Assistant Curator and Acting Curator. Records consist primarily of correspondence regarding prospective Museum acquisitions. Items of special interest include letters concerning the Museum’s acquisition of early American colonial furnishings, later displayed in the American Wing.
  Biographical/Historical note
  Curator and artist Durr Friedley (1888-1938) was born in Indianapolis, Indiana and received a degree in Fine Arts from Harvard University in 1911. (At Harvard and later in life his surname was spelled Freedley; in records from his time at the Metropolitan Museum of Art it consistently appears as Friedley.) He joined the staff of the Metropolitan Museum of Art in October, 1911, as an assistant in the Department of Decorative Arts. In 1912, after favorable recommendations by colleagues, Friedley was appointed Assistant Curator. He was promoted to Acting Curator in 1914 when the department’s Curator, Dr. Wilhelm R. Valentiner, took a leave of absence to enlist in the German army. Valentiner resigned from the Metropolitan in 1917 and Friedley was offered the post of Curator, but he declined and instead announced his own departure from the Museum.
  During his time at the Museum, Friedley was involved with the acquisition and exhibition of a wide range of decorative arts objects. He corresponded extensively with collectors and dealers who owned items of interest to the Museum, and assessed objects under consideration by the Purchasing Committee of the Board of Trustees. Towards the end of his tenure, he worked intensively on the acquisition of colonial American interiors and objects intended for exhibition in the Museum’s planned American Wing. Shortly after leaving the Metropolitan, Friedley drew a set of architectural plans for the proposed American Wing, but they were never used.
  Friedley served in the U.S. armed forces [branch, dates?] where he painted camouflage on war planes. In the 1920s, he spent time in Europe as a portrait painter. He eventually returned to the United States and settled in Newport, Rhode Island, where he continued his career as a portrait painter and muralist. Friedley died in a car accident at the age of fifty. A memorial exhibit of his artwork was held at the Walker Galleries in New York City in early 1939.
  Scope and Contents note
  Records include letters regarding potential Museum acquisitions exchanged by Durr Friedley with dealers and private owners of decorative arts objects. The bulk of this correspondence is over Friedley’s own signature, but there are also some letters from the desks of other Decorative Arts Department staff, notably Assistant Curator Russell A. Plimpton (see Series 2). Prominent dealers and collectors represented include Duveen Brothers, Judge A.T Clearwater and White, Allom and Company. There are a few personal letters, and a small amount of correspondences from before and after Friedley’s service at the Museum. Also included are collection inventory lists, handwritten notes regarding museum objects, photographs and typescript essays by Friedley and other Museum staff. There is substantial documentation regarding the acquisition by the Museum of colonial interiors and period rooms, and planning for the proposed American Wing. The records also include correspondence between Friedley and other members of the Museum administration including Secretary Henry Watson Kent and Director Edward Robinson.
  - A, 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - B, 1916-1918 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - C, 1915-1918 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Clark, Charles C., 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Clearwater, Hon. A.T., 1918 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - D, 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - E, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - F, 1916-1918 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - G, 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - H, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - I, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - K, 1915-1916 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Kent, Henry W., 1916 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - L, 1915-1917 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Lowndes, Mrs. Stanley, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - M, 1915-1917 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Mexican Majolica, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous notes, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - N, 1916-1917 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - O, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - P, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Pitcairn, Raymond, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Q, 1917-1918 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - R, 1916-1918 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Robinson, Edward (Director), 1916-1917 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - S, 1915-1918 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Silver, 1914-1918 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Silver, notes on, n.d (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - T, 1915-1917 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - V, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - W, 1915-1917 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Y, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 22)